IRVING GÓMEZ MÉNDEZ

https://irvinggomez.com

https://github.com/IrvingGomez

✓ gomendez.irving@gmail.com

Pathum Thani, Thailand

Summary

I am a data scientist that merges the experience in applied statistics with a solid theoretical background in machine learning (random forests, neural networks, support vector machines, recommender systems, etc.) and statistics (inference, regression, Bayesian statistics, multivariate analysis, etc.), who enjoys passing from theory to development of meaningful tech products.

A portfolio of past and current projects, talks and courses can be found at https://irvinggomez.com while their respective codes can be found at https://github.com/IrvingGomez.

Computing Skills

Programming Languages: Python, Julia, R Data Visualization: Plotly, Tableau, Shiny

Deep Learning: TensorFlow Big Data: PySpark Bayesian Analysis: **PvMC**

SPSS, Google Analytics Other Data Analysis: Other Languages: SQL, HTML, CSS, LATEX

Professional Experience

National Electronics and Computer Technology Center (NECTEC), Thailand Postdoctoral Researcher

March 2023 - To date

- Bayesian data analysis to assist policy makers.
- Data wrangling of large data sets for its further statistical analysis.

Universidad Iberoamericana (Ibero-American University)

Lecturer

August 2021 - To date

- Development and improvement of actuarial subjects' syllabus.
- Teaching undergraduate subjects: Bayesian statistics, machine learning, actuarial probability.

Banco del Bajío (Bajio Bank)

Sr. Data Scientist

July 2021 - February 2023

- Implementation of models in an AutoML framework.
- Improvement of statistical tools for internal fraud detection.
- Translate business and customer needs to technical language to determine the best model and solution.
- Present results and projects' progress on an executive level.
- Development of end-to-end projects to evaluate prospects' credit risk.
- Data wrangling and feature engineering from large databases, merging public and private information sources of heterogeneous data.
- Implementation and evaluation of algorithms to estimate the stability of economic sectors.
- Robust statistical inference to improve prospects' estimations.
- Geo-statistical analysis to help in decision making.

Centro de Investigación en Matemáticas (Center for Research in Mathematics, CIMAT) Postgraduate Student in Probability and Statistics

August 2014 - June 2021

- Development and implementation of state-of-the-art random forests algorithms to handle data with missing values
- Implementation of neural networks for recommender systems with partial information.
- Development of methodologies for detection of illegal traffic of species in America.
- Implementation of methodologies for control quality with heavily censored data.
- Statistical consulting for the automotive industry, improving its warranty management.
- Reliability analysis for the food industry, increasing preference of consumers.
- Teaching assistant in undergraduate and graduate subjects: Statistical inference, statistical models.

OPI Analytics

Sr. Data Scientist

August 2020 - December 2020

- Development and improvement of end-to-end projects for sale's forecasts.
- Monitor and validation of building blocks.
- Automation of data science processes.
- Validation of pricing strategies.

Academic Qualifications

David Sprott Award, 2015

Annual prize granted by the Centro de Investigación en Matemáticas (CIMAT) to the best master's exam in the area of statistics.

Publications

Gómez-Méndez, Irving and Chainarong Amornbunchornvej (2023). "Income, education, and other poverty-related variables: a journey through Bayesian hierarchical models". In: arXiv preprint arXiv:2308.16578.

Gómez-Méndez, Irving and Emilien Joly (2023a). "On the consistency of a random forest algorithm in the presence of missing entries". In: *Journal of Nonparametric Statistics*. DOI: 10.1080/10485252.2023.2219783.

Gómez-Méndez, Irving and Emilien Joly (2023b). "Regression with missing data, a comparison study of techniques based on random forests". In: *Journal of Statistical Computation and Simulation*. DOI: 10.1080/00949655.2022. 2163646.

Selected Talks

01/2022

Mathematical Association of Cambodia (MAC), Virtual $An\ Introduction\ to\ Causality$

12/2020

Hispanohablante Seminar, Guanajuato

 $Consistency\ of\ a\ Random\ Forest\ Algorithm\ with\ Missing\ Entries$

03/2020

Inria Sequel Seminar, Lille

Some ideas for random forests with missing values 01/2020

TRIPODS workshop CIMAT-University of Arizona, Guanajuato

Some ideas for random forests with missing values

Certifications

Google Analytics
Data Sets with SQL
SQL for Data Science
Statistical Analysis with SPSS

Languages

Spanish Native English Fluent Portuguese Fluent French Basic

Thai Elemental (learning)